The writer George Eliot cautioned us that,
حذّرتنا المؤلّفة جورج إيليوت أنّ
among all forms of mistake,
من ضمن مختلف أنواع الأخطاء،
prophesy is the most gratuitous.
التّنبؤ هو الأسوأ.
The person that we would all acknowledge
و الشّخص الذي نعتبره ندّا لها
as her 20th-century counterpart, Yogi Berra, agreed.
في القرن العشرين، يوغي بيرا يوافقها الرأي.
He said, "It's tough to make predictions,
لقد قال:"إنّه من الصعب أن نقوم بتنبّؤات،
especially about the future."
خاصّة عن المستقبل."
I'm going to ignore their cautions
لكنني سأتجاهل تحذيراتهم
and make one very specific forecast.
و أقوم بعرض خاصّ جدّا.
In the world that we are creating very quickly,
في العالم الذي نقوم ببناءه بشكل سريع،
we're going to see more and more things
سوف نرى العديد من الأمور
that look like science fiction,
التي تبدو كأنّها من الخيال العلميّ،
and fewer and fewer things that look like jobs.
و أقلّ أمورا تبدو كأنّها مهن.
Our cars are very quickly going to start driving themselves,
سوف تبدأ سيّاراتنا سريعا في السياقة الذاتية،
which means we're going to need fewer truck drivers.
ممّا يعني أنّنا سنحتاج عددا أقلّ من سائقي الشاحنات.
We're going to hook Siri up to Watson
سنقوم بالربط بين سيري و واطسون
and use that to automate a lot of the work
مستخدمين ذلك لأتمتة العديد من العمل
that's currently done by customer service reps
الذي يقوم به حاليّا مندوبو خدمة الزّبائن،
and troubleshooters and diagnosers,
و مكتشفو الأخطاء و المحلّلون،
and we're already taking R2D2,
نحن بالفعل نأخذ روبوت R2D2،
painting him orange, and putting him to work
نطليه بالبرتقاليّ، و نضع يعمل
carrying shelves around warehouses,
حاملا الرّفوف في المخازن
which means we need a lot fewer people
ممّا يعني نقص حاجتنا لأشخاص
to be walking up and down those aisles.
للقيام بذلك الدّور.
Now, for about 200 years,
لمدّة 200 سنة،
people have been saying exactly what I'm telling you --
كان النّاس يردّدون ما كنت أقوله لتوّي -
the age of technological unemployment is at hand —
إنّه عصر التكنولوجيا المسبّبة للبطالة -
starting with the Luddites smashing looms in Britain
بدءا من حركة اللاضية في بريطانيا
just about two centuries ago,
منذ 200 سنة مضت،
and they have been wrong.
و قد كانوا مخطئين.
Our economies in the developed world have coasted along
اقتصاديّاتنا بالبلدان المتقدّمة استفادت
on something pretty close to full employment.
من التّشغيل الكامل.
Which brings up a critical question:
ممّا يجعلنا نطرح سؤالا هامّا:
Why is this time different, if it really is?
لما الأمر مختلف هذه المرّة، إن كان بالفعل مختلفا؟
The reason it's different is that, just in the past few years,
السبب في كونه مختلف هو أنّ الآلات
our machines have started demonstrating skills
قد بدأت تكشف في السنوات الأخيرة عن امكانيّات
they have never, ever had before:
لم تكن تمتلكها مطلقا في السابق:
understanding, speaking, hearing, seeing,
الفهم، التحدّث، الاستماع، الرّؤية،
answering, writing, and they're still acquiring new skills.
الإجابة، الكتابة، ولا تزال بصدد اكتساب مهارات جديدة.
For example, mobile humanoid robots
لنأخذ مثال الروبوتات المتنقلة
are still incredibly primitive,
فهي لا تزال بدائيّة،
but the research arm of the Defense Department
لكن فريق البحث بوزارة الدفاع
just launched a competition
أطلق لتوّه مسابقة
to have them do things like this,
لجعلها تقوم بأمور مماثلة،
and if the track record is any guide,
وإن كنّا سنستدلّ بسجلّ المتابعة،
this competition is going to be successful.
هذه المسابقة ستكون ناجحة.
So when I look around, I think the day is not too far off at all
عندما انظر حولي، أفكّر أنّ ذلك اليوم ليس ببعيد
when we're going to have androids
يوم يكون لنا روبوتات مشابهة للبشر
doing a lot of the work that we are doing right now.
تحتلّ العديد من المواقع التي نعمل بها الآن.
And we're creating a world where there is going to be
ونحن بصدد بناء عالم سيكون فيه
more and more technology and fewer and fewer jobs.
أعداد متزايدة من التكنولوجيا و أعداد متناقصة من المهن.
It's a world that Erik Brynjolfsson and I are calling
إنّه عالم أطلقت عليه أنا و إيريك برينجولف تسمية
"the new machine age."
"عصر الآلة الجديد".
The thing to keep in mind is that
الشيء الذي يجب أن نأخذه بعين الاعتبار هو
this is absolutely great news.
أنّ هذه أخبار سارّة.
This is the best economic news on the planet these days.
هذا أفضل نبأ اقتصادي على الكوكب في أيامنا هذه.
Not that there's a lot of competition, right?
غير أن هناك الكثير من المنافسة، أليس كذلك؟
This is the best economic news we have these days
هذا من أفضل الأخبار الاقتصادية لدينا هذه الأيام
for two main reasons.
وذلك لسببين رئيسيين.
The first is, technological progress is what allows us
أوّلا، التقدم التكنولوجي هو الذي يسمح لنا
to continue this amazing recent run that we're on
بمواصلة هذا التطور المذعل الذي نحن فيه
where output goes up over time,
حيث المردود يرتفع مع مرور الزمن،
while at the same time, prices go down,
و في الوقت نفسه، الأسعار تنخفض،
and volume and quality just continue to explode.
و يتواصل تحسن الحجم والنوعية.
Now, some people look at this and talk about
بعض الناس ينظرون إلى هذا ويتحدثون عن
shallow materialism,
المادية السطحيّة،
but that's absolutely the wrong way to look at it.
ولكن هذه طريقة خاطئة للنّظر في الموضوع.
This is abundance, which is exactly
هذه هي الوفرة، وهي بالضبط
what we want our economic system to provide.
ما نريد أن نوفّره لنظامنا الاقتصادي.
The second reason that the new machine age
السبب الثاني هو أنّ عصر الآلة الجديد
is such great news is that, once the androids
و ما إن يبدأ الرجال الآليون
start doing jobs, we don't have to do them anymore,
القيام بالوظائف، لا يتوجّب علينا القيام بها بعد الآن،
and we get freed up from drudgery and toil.
و نتحرّر من الكدح والكد.
Now, when I talk about this with my friends
عندما أتحدث عن هذا مع أصدقائي
in Cambridge and Silicon Valley, they say,
في كامبردج ووادي السليكون، يقولون،
"Fantastic. No more drudgery, no more toil.
"رائع. لا مزيد من العمل الشاق، لا مزيد من الكد."
This gives us the chance to imagine
وهذا يعطينا فرصة لتخيُّل
an entirely different kind of society,
نوع مختلف تماما من المجتمع،
a society where the creators and the discoverers
مجتمع حيث المبدعون والمكتشفون
and the performers and the innovators
و فنانو الأداء والمبدعون
come together with their patrons and their financiers
يقفون جنبا إلى جنب مع مدرائهم و الممولين
to talk about issues, entertain, enlighten,
للحديث عن القضايا، الترفيه، و التنوير،
provoke each other."
و استفزاز بعضهم البعض ".
It's a society really, that looks a lot like the TED Conference.
إنّه حقاً مجتمع مشابه لمؤتمر TED.
And there's actually a huge amount of truth here.
وهناك في الواقع الكثير من الحقائق هنا.
We are seeing an amazing flourishing taking place.
نحن بصدد رؤية ازدهار مذهل.
In a world where it is just about as easy
في عالم حيث إنشاء شيء هو بسهولة
to generate an object as it is to print a document,
طباعة وثائق،
we have amazing new possibilities.
لدينا إمكانيات جديدة مدهشة.
The people who used to be craftsmen and hobbyists
الناس الذين كانوا حرفيين و هواة
are now makers, and they're responsible
أصبحوا الآن صنّاعا، و مسؤولون
for massive amounts of innovation.
على العديد من الابتكارات.
And artists who were formerly constrained
والفنانون الذين كانوا مقيّدين سابقا
can now do things that were never, ever possible
يمكنهم الآن القيام بالأشياء التي لم تكن متاحة لهم،
for them before.
لهم سابقا.
So this is a time of great flourishing,
لذلك هذا زمن ازدهار كبير،
and the more I look around, the more convinced I become
وكلّما ألقي نظرة حولي، أصبح مقتنعا أكثر
that this quote, from the physicist Freeman Dyson,
بأنّ هذا الاقتباس من الفيزيائي "فريمان دايسون"،
is not hyperbole at all.
ليس مبالغا فيه على الإطلاق.
This is just a plain statement of the facts.
هذا مجرد سرد عاديّ للوقائع.
We are in the middle of an astonishing period.
نحن في منتصف فترة مذهلة.
["Technology is a gift of God. After the gift of life it is perhaps the greatest of God's gifts. It is the mother of civilizations, of arts and of sciences." — Freeman Dyson]
["التكنولوجيا هبة الله. هي ربما من أعظم هبات الله بعد هبة الحياة. هي أمّ الحضارات والفنون والعلوم. "— فريمان دايسون]
Which brings up another great question:
ممّا يجعلنا نتساءل:
What could possibly go wrong in this new machine age?
ماذا يمكن أن يسوء في عصر الآلة الجديد؟
Right? Great, hang up, flourish, go home.
أليس كذلك؟ انتظر، ازدهر ثمّ عد إلى البيت.
We're going to face two really thorny sets of challenges
سنجد أنفسنا في مواجهة مجموعتين من التحديات
as we head deeper into the future that we're creating.
كلّما غصنا أعمق نحو المستقبل الذي تقوم بإنشاءه.
The first are economic, and they're really nicely summarized
أولا، تحديات اقتصادية، و هي ملخّصة بطريقة رائعة
in an apocryphal story about a back-and-forth
في قصة ملفقة حول جدال دار بين
between Henry Ford II and Walter Reuther,
هنري فورد الثاني و والتر رويتر،
who was the head of the auto workers union.
الذي كان رئيس اتحاد عمال السيارات.
They were touring one of the new modern factories,
كان الرجلان يقومان بجولة في أحد المصانع الحديثة الجديدة،
and Ford playfully turns to Reuther and says,
فنظر فورد إلى رويتر قائلا،
"Hey Walter, how are you going to get these robots
"يا والتر، كيف ستجعل هذه الروبوتات
to pay union dues?"
تدفع الرسوم النقابية "؟
And Reuther shoots back, "Hey Henry,
فيجيبه رويتر، "يا هنري،
how are you going to get them to buy cars?"
كيف ستجعلهم يقتنون السيارات؟ "
Reuther's problem in that anecdote
مشكلة رويتر في هذه القصة
is that it is tough to offer your labor to an economy
هو أنّه من الصعب تقديم عملك في ظل اقتصاد
that's full of machines,
يعتمد بصفة كاملة على الآلات،
and we see this very clearly in the statistics.
و الإحصاءات تبيّن هذا جيدا.
If you look over the past couple decades
إذا قمت بالبحث في العقود القليلة الماضية
at the returns to capital -- in other words, corporate profits --
عوائد رؤوس الأموال- أو بعبارة أخرى، أرباح الشركات-
we see them going up,
سنراهم في تصاعد،
and we see that they're now at an all-time high.
ونحن نرى أنّهم الآن بلغوا أعلى مستوى على الإطلاق.
If we look at the returns to labor, in other words
إذا ألقينا نظرة على عوائد العمل، أو بعبارة أخرى
total wages paid out in the economy,
مجموع الأجور المدفوعة في الاقتصاد،
we see them at an all-time low
سنراهم في أدنى مستوياتها
and heading very quickly in the opposite direction.
متّجهة بسرعة فائقة نحو الاتجاه المعاكس.
So this is clearly bad news for Reuther.
لذا من الواضح أنّ هذه الأخبار سيئة لرويتر.
It looks like it might be great news for Ford,
يبدو الأمر كما لو أنّه قد يكون نبأ سارّا بالنّسبة فورد،
but it's actually not. If you want to sell
لكنه ليس كذلك في الواقع. إذا كنت ترغب في بيع
huge volumes of somewhat expensive goods to people,
كميات ضخمة من السلع الباهظة الثمن للنّاس،
you really want a large, stable, prosperous middle class.
ستحتاج وجود طبقة وسطى كبيرة و مستقرة و مزدهرة.
We have had one of those in America
كان لدينا واحدة مماثلة في أمريكا
for just about the entire postwar period.
فقط طيلة فترة ما بعد الحرب.
But the middle class is clearly under huge threat right now.
ولكن من الواضح أن الطبقة الوسطى تحت تهديد كبير الآن.
We all know a lot of the statistics,
ونحن جميعا نعرف الكثير من الإحصائيات،
but just to repeat one of them,
لكن فقط لأذكّركم بإحداها،
median income in America has actually gone down
في الواقع قد انخفض متوسط الدخل في أمريكا
over the past 15 years,
على مدى السنوات ال 15 الماضية،
and we're in danger of getting trapped
ونحن في خطر الوقوع في
in some vicious cycle where inequality and polarization
حلقة مفرغة حيث التفاوت والاستقطاب
continue to go up over time.
سترتفعان مع مرور الوقت.
The societal challenges that come along
التحديات المجتمعية التي تظهر
with that kind of inequality deserve some attention.
مع هذا النوع من عدم المساواة تستحق بعض الاهتمام.
There are a set of societal challenges
وهناك مجموعة من التحديات المجتمعية
that I'm actually not that worried about,
التي لا تجعلني قلقا في الواقع،
and they're captured by images like this.
و هي ملتقطة في صور كهذه.
This is not the kind of societal problem
ليس هذا نوع المشاكل المجتمعية
that I am concerned about.
التي أنا قلق بشأنها.
There is no shortage of dystopian visions
لن تقلّ تلك النظرات اليائسة
about what happens when our machines become self-aware,
حول ما يحدث عندما تصبح آلاتنا واعية بذاتها،
and they decide to rise up and coordinate attacks against us.
و قررت أن تثور، وتنسّق هجمات ضدنا.
I'm going to start worrying about those
أنا سأبدأ بالقلق بهذا الشأن
the day my computer becomes aware of my printer.
يوم يصبح جهاز الكمبيوتر الخاص بي واعيا بالطابعة.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So this is not the set of challenges we really need to worry about.
هذه ليست التحديات التي نحن بحاجة للقلق حولها.
To tell you the kinds of societal challenges
لأخبركم عن أنواع التحديات المجتمعية
that are going to come up in the new machine age,
التي سوف تظهر في عصر الآلة الجديد،
I want to tell a story about two stereotypical American workers.
أريد أن تروي قصة عن عاملين أمريكيّين عاديّين.
And to make them really stereotypical,
و لجعل الشخصيّتين نمطيّتين،
let's make them both white guys.
دعونا نجعل كلاّ منهما من الرجال البيض.
And the first one is a college-educated
الأول دارس بالجامعة
professional, creative type, manager,
متمرّس، من النوع المبدع، مدير،
engineer, doctor, lawyer, that kind of worker.
مهندس، طبيب، محام، هذا النوع من العمال.
We're going to call him "Ted."
سنسمّيه "تيد".
He's at the top of the American middle class.
وهو ينتمي للجزء العلوي من الطبقة الوسطى الأمريكية.
His counterpart is not college-educated
الثاني لم يدرس في الجامعة
and works as a laborer, works as a clerk,
يشتغل كعامل، يعمل ككاتب،
does low-level white collar or blue collar work in the economy.
و أعمال الياقات البيضاء و الياقات الزرقاء المنخفضة المستوى في الاقتصاد.
We're going to call that guy "Bill."
سندعوه "بيل".
And if you go back about 50 years,
إن عدنا بالزمن 50 سنة مضت،
Bill and Ted were leading remarkably similar lives.
سيكون ل"تيد" و "بيل" حياة متشابهة.
For example, in 1960 they were both very likely
على سبيل المثال، في عام 1960 كان من المرجح جداً أنّ كلا منهما
to have full-time jobs, working at least 40 hours a week.
له وظيفة بدوام كامل، و يعمل على الأقل 40 ساعة في الأسبوع.
But as the social researcher Charles Murray has documented,
ولكن الباحث الاجتماعي تشارلز موراي قام بتوثيق،
as we started to automate the economy,
أنّ بداية ظهور أتمتة الاقتصاد،
and 1960 is just about when computers started to be used by businesses,
وعام 1960 تقريبا عندما بدأت الشركات تستخدم أجهزة الكمبيوتر،
as we started to progressively inject technology
و عند البدأ تدريجيّا في إدخال التكنولوجيا
and automation and digital stuff into the economy,
والتشغيل الآلي للمكاتب والأشياء الرقمية في الاقتصاد،
the fortunes of Bill and Ted diverged a lot.
تباينت حظوظ "تيد" و "بيل" كثيرا.
Over this time frame, Ted has continued
خلال هذا الإطار الزمني، تيد واصل
to hold a full-time job. Bill hasn't.
الاشتغال بوظيفة بدوام كامل، عكس "بيل".
In many cases, Bill has left the economy entirely,
في كثير من الحالات، قد يكون "بيل" قد ترك الاقتصاد تماما،
and Ted very rarely has.
و من النادر جدا أن يكون "تيد" قد فعل.
Over time, Ted's marriage has stayed quite happy.
على مرّ الزمن، بقي زواج "تيد" سعيداً.
Bill's hasn't.
العكس حصل ل"بيل".
And Ted's kids have grown up in a two-parent home,
وقد كبر أطفال "تيد" في منزل يضمّ الأبوين،
while Bill's absolutely have not over time.
عكس أبناء "بيل" على الأرجح.
Other ways that Bill is dropping out of society?
هل من طرق أخرى يبتعد بها "بيل" عن إطار المجتمع؟
He's decreased his voting in presidential elections,
انخفضت نسبة مشاركته في التصويت في الانتخابات الرئاسية،
and he's started to go to prison a lot more often.
وقد بدأ يدخل السجن في الكثير من الأحيان.
So I cannot tell a happy story about these social trends,
لذا لا يمكنني أن أحكي قصة سعيدة إزاء هذه الاتجاهات الاجتماعية،
and they don't show any signs of reversing themselves.
وهم لا يبدون أيّ علامات تحسّن.
They're also true no matter which ethnic group
الأمر صحيح مهما تكن المجموعة العرقية
or demographic group we look at,
أو المجموعة السكانية التي نقوم بمراقبتها،
and they're actually getting so severe
و الأمر يزداد سوءا
that they're in danger of overwhelming
و هم في خطر حتّى على
even the amazing progress we made with the Civil Rights Movement.
التقدم المذهل الذي قمنا به بفضل حركة الحقوق المدنية.
And what my friends in Silicon Valley
و أصدقائي من سيليكون فالي
and Cambridge are overlooking is that they're Ted.
و كامبريدج غافلون عن كونهم "تيد".
They're living these amazingly busy, productive lives,
إنّهم يعيشون نمط حياة منشغلة و انتاجية،
and they've got all the benefits to show from that,
و هم يحصلون على جميع الفوائد التي يتحصلون عليها،
while Bill is leading a very different life.
في حين يعيش "بيل" حياة مختلفة جداً.
They're actually both proof of how right Voltaire was
إنهم في الواقع دليل على صحّة فولتير
when he talked about the benefits of work,
عندما تحدث عن مزايا العمل،
and the fact that it saves us from not one but three great evils.
وحقيقة أنّه يحمينا من 3 شرور عظيمة.
["Work saves a man from three great evils: boredom, vice and need." — Voltaire]
["العمل يحفظ رجل من شرور 3 كبيرة: الضجر، الرذيلة والحاجة." — فولتير]
So with these challenges, what do we do about them?
ما نحن فاعلون بشأن هذه التحديات؟
The economic playbook is surprisingly clear,
قواعد اللعبة الاقتصادية واضحة لدرجة تثير الاستغراب،
surprisingly straightforward, in the short term especially.
هي مباشرة و صريحة، خاصة على المدى القريب.
The robots are not going to take all of our jobs in the next year or two,
الروبوتات لن تأخذ كل من وظائفنا في العام القادم أو العامين القادمين،
so the classic Econ 101 playbook is going to work just fine:
إذن كتاب قواعد الاقتصاد للمبتدئين سيعمل على ما يرام:
Encourage entrepreneurship,
تشجيع روح المبادرة،
double down on infrastructure,
تضاعف في البنية التحتية،
and make sure we're turning out people
التأكد من تحويل وجهة الأشخاص
from our educational system with the appropriate skills.
من النظام التعليمي إلى مياديين بالمهارات المناسبة.
But over the longer term, if we are moving into an economy
ولكن على المدى الطويل، إذا أردنا الانتقال إلى اقتصاد
that's heavy on technology and light on labor,
يكون معتمدا أكثر على التكنولوجيا و أقل على العمّال،
and we are, then we have to consider
ونحن بالفعل في تلك المرحلة، فعلينا أن
some more radical interventions,
نفكّر بالقيام ببعض التدخلات الجذرية،
for example, something like a guaranteed minimum income.
على سبيل المثال، شيء من قبيل ضمان الحد أدنى من الدّخل.
Now, that's probably making some folk in this room uncomfortable,
هذا على الأرجح جعل بعضا من الجالسين بهذه القاعة منزعجين
because that idea is associated with the extreme left wing
لأنّ هذه الفكرة مقترنة مع اليسار المتطرف
and with fairly radical schemes for redistributing wealth.
ومع مخططات جذريّة إلى حدّ ما لإعادة توزيع الثروات.
I did a little bit of research on this notion,
أجريت القليل من البحوث بشأن هذه الفكرة،
and it might calm some folk down to know that
و يمكن لمعرفة هذا أن يقوم بتهدئتكم:
the idea of a net guaranteed minimum income
فكرة إنشاء شبكة ضمان الحد الأدنى من الدخل
has been championed by those frothing-at-the-mouth socialists
كانت مدعومة من قبل العديد من الاشتراكيين مثل
Friedrich Hayek, Richard Nixon and Milton Friedman.
فريدريك حايك و ريتشارد نيكسون و ميلتون فريدمان.
And if you find yourself worried
وإذا كنت تجد نفسك قلقا
that something like a guaranteed income
أنّ شيئا من قبيل ضمان الدخل
is going to stifle our drive to succeed
سيكبت سعينا الحثيث لتحقيق النجاح
and make us kind of complacent,
و يجعلنا راضين عن أنفسنا،
you might be interested to know that social mobility,
قد تكون مهتما لمعرفة أن الحراك الاجتماعي،
one of the things we really pride ourselves on in the United States,
هو من أحد الأمور التي تعدّ حقاً مصدر فخر في الولايات المتحدة،
is now lower than it is in the northern European countries
وهو الآن أقل مما عليه في بلدان أوروبا الشمالية
that have these very generous social safety nets.
التي تحتوي على هذه شبكات من السلامة الاجتماعية سخيّة جداً.
So the economic playbook is actually pretty straightforward.
لذلك قواعد اللعبة الاقتصادية واضحة جداً في الواقع.
The societal one is a lot more challenging.
أمّا المجتمعية فهي أكثر تحدّيا.
I don't know what the playbook is
أنا لا أعرف ما القواعد التي
for getting Bill to engage and stay engaged throughout life.
ستجعل "بيل" يلتزم ويصمد طوال الحياة.
I do know that education is a huge part of it.
أنا أعرف أنّ التعليم جزء كبير منه.
I witnessed this firsthand.
ولقد شهدت ذلك مباشرة.
I was a Montessori kid for the first few years of my education,
كنت طفلا من مونتيسوري في أولى سنوات دراستي،
and what that education taught me
وما علّمني إيّاه ذلك التعليم
is that the world is an interesting place
هو أنّ العالم مكان مثير للاهتمام
and my job is to go explore it.
ومهمّتي هي استكشافه.
The school stopped in third grade,
توقّفت عن المدرسة في الصف الثالث،
so then I entered the public school system,
ثمّ دخلت في نظام المدارس العامة،
and it felt like I had been sent to the Gulag.
وشعرت أنّه قد تمّ إرسالي إلى معسكرات العمل.
With the benefit of hindsight, I now know the job
مع الاستفادة من تجاربنا السابقة، الآن أعرف أنّ مهمتي
was to prepare me for life as a clerk or a laborer,
هو الاستعداد للحياة ككاتب أو عامل يومي،
but at the time it felt like the job was to kind of
و لكن في الوقت نفسه أحسست أنّه كان جعلني
bore me into some submission with what was going on around me.
في وضعيّة خضوع نوعا ما مع كلّ ما كان يدور حولي.
We have to do better than this.
علينا أن نفعل ما هو أفضل من هذا.
We cannot keep turning out Bills.
لا يجب أن نواصل انتاج أشخاص ك"بيل".
So we see some green shoots that things are getting better.
نحن نرى بعض البراعم الخضراء التي ستكون أفضل.
We see technology deeply impacting education
نحن نرى التكنولوجيا بالغة التأثير على التعليم
and engaging people, from our youngest learners
وإشراك الناس، من أصغر المتعلمين لدينا
up to our oldest ones.
إلى أكبرهم.
We see very prominent business voices telling us
ونحن نرى أصواتا بارزة جداً من الأعمال التي تقول لنا
we need to rethink some of the things that we've been holding dear for a while.
نحن بحاجة إلى إعادة التفكير في بعض الأمور التي كنّا نعزّها لفترة من الوقت.
And we see very serious and sustained
و نحن نرى جهودا خطيرة ومتواصلة
and data-driven efforts to understand
و مبنية على البيانات لمحاولة فهم
how to intervene in some of the most troubled communities that we have.
كيفية التّدخل في بعض المجتمعات الأكثر اضطرابا لدينا.
So the green shoots are out there.
إذن، البراعم الخضراء موجودة هناك.
I don't want to pretend for a minute
لا أرغب في التظاهر لمدة دقيقة
that what we have is going to be enough.
أنّ ما لدينا على وشك أن يكون كافياً.
We're facing very tough challenges.
إنّنا نواجه تحديات صعبة للغاية.
To give just one example, there are about five million Americans
لإعطاء مثال واحد فقط، هناك حوالي 5 مليون من الأمريكيين
who have been unemployed for at least six months.
الذين كانوا عاطلين عن العمل لمدة ستة أشهر على الأقل.
We're not going to fix things for them
لن نقوم بإصلاح الأمور بالنسبة لهم
by sending them back to Montessori.
عن طريق إرسالهم مجددا إلى مونتيسوري.
And my biggest worry is that we're creating a world
وقلقي الأكبر أنّنا بصدد خلق عالم
where we're going to have glittering technologies
حيث ستكون هناك تكنولوجيا متقدّمة
embedded in kind of a shabby society
موجودة في مجتمع متدنّ
and supported by an economy that generates inequality
ومدعوم باقتصاد يقوم بخلق عدم المساواة
instead of opportunity.
بدلاً من الفرص.
But I actually don't think that's what we're going to do.
ولكن في الواقع لا أعتقد أنّ هذا ما نحن بصدد القيام به.
I think we're going to do something a lot better
وأعتقد أننا في طريقنا إلى القيام بشيء أفضل بكثير
for one very straightforward reason:
لسبب بسيط جداً:
The facts are getting out there.
إليكم بعض الحقائق.
The realities of this new machine age
الحقائق حول هذا العصر الجديد للآلة
and the change in the economy are becoming more widely known.
والتغيير في الاقتصاد أصبحا معروفين على نطاق واسع.
If we wanted to accelerate that process, we could do things
إذا أردنا لتعجيل بهذه العملية، يمكن أن نقوم أشياء
like have our best economists and policymakers
مثل جعل أفضل الاقتصاديين و واضعي السياسات
play "Jeopardy!" against Watson.
يلعبون لعبة "المحك" ضد واتسون.
We could send Congress on an autonomous car road trip.
ويمكننا أن نرسل الكونغرس في رحلة طريق سيارة ذاتيّة التحكم.
And if we do enough of these kinds of things,
و إن قمنا بما فيه الكفاية لمثل هذه الأمور،
the awareness is going to sink in that things are going to be different.
الوعي يتّجه نحو فهم أنّ الأمور ستكون مختلفة.
And then we're off to the races,
ومن ثم نحن سنقوم بسباقات،
because I don't believe for a second
لأنني لا أعتقد أبدا
that we have forgotten how to solve tough challenges
أننا نسينا كيفية مواجهة التحديات الصعبة
or that we have become too apathetic or hard-hearted to even try.
أو أن أصبحنا لا مبالين لدرجة أن لا نحاول.
I started my talk with quotes from wordsmiths
لقد بدأت حديثي مع اقتباسات من أدباء ملهمين
who were separated by an ocean and a century.
كان يفصلهم البحر و قرن كامل من الزمن.
Let me end it with words from politicians
واسمحوا لي أن أنهي بكلمات من السياسييّن
who were similarly distant.
الذين كانوا فعلا متباعدين.
Winston Churchill came to my home of MIT in 1949,
ونستون تشرشل، جاء إلى معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا في عام 1949،
and he said, "If we are to bring the broad masses
وقال، "إذا ما أردنا أن نجلب الجماهير العريضة
of the people in every land to the table of abundance,
للشعوب في كل الأراضي إلى جدول الوفرة،
it can only be by the tireless improvement
فذلك ممكن فقط عبر تحسين دؤوب
of all of our means of technical production."
لكل إمكانياتنا للإنتاج الفنيّ".
Abraham Lincoln realized there was one other ingredient.
أبراهام لينكولن أدرك أنّ هناك عنصرا آخر.
He said, "I am a firm believer in the people.
لقد قال "أنا أشد المؤمنين في الشعب.
If given the truth, they can be depended upon
إذا تمّ اعطاؤهم الحقيقة، يمكن الاعتماد عليهم
to meet any national crisis.
لمواجهة أي أزمة وطنية.
The great point is to give them the plain facts."
المهمّ أن نعطيهم الحقائق".
So the optimistic note, great point that I want to leave you with
إذن أترككم مع ملاحظة متفائلة
is that the plain facts of the machine age are becoming clear,
هو أنّ حقائق العصر الجديد للآلة أصبحت واضحة،
and I have every confidence that we're going to use them
ولديّ كل الثقة بأننا سوف نستعملها
to chart a good course into the challenging,
لرسم مسار جيد في التحدي،
abundant economy that we're creating.
الاقتصاد الوفيرة التي نحن بصدد إنشاءه.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)